Howard W. and Jean Lipman
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Howard W. and Jean Lipman papers
1848, 1916-2000
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Lipman, Howard
46.2 linear feet
The Howard W. and Jean Lipman papers measure 46.2 linear feet and span the years 1916 to 2000, with one brochure maintained in a research file dating to 1848. The bulk dates for the collection are 1932 to 1992. The papers primarily concern the art collecting activities and interests of the Lipmans which included modern American sculpture, American folk art, and other contemporary American paintings. Found within the papers are correspondence files, notes and printed material that served as research and reference material, along with financial material. The collection also contains writings, notes, and editorial material used by Jean Lipman in her dual roles as an editor for Art in America magazine and as a respected art critic and author.
Biographical Note
Howard W. and Jean Lipman shared a lifetime sponsorship of art. The Lipman's personal art collection, acquired throughout their marriage, was eventually divided into three separate parts: The Howard W. Lipman Foundation collection that was donated and merged into the modern sculpture holdings of the Whitney Museum of American Art; an American folk art collection that was later sold through two separate auctions in 1950 and 1981 and is now part of the holdings of the New York Historical Association and the Museum of American Folk Art; and a personal collection that was retained and displayed in the Lipmans' various residences in Connecticut, New York, and Arizona.
Married in 1933, the Lipmans began jointly collecting American folk art at a time when few art museums or institutions recognized the historical and artistic value of early primitive, self-taught artists. By the late 1940s, the Lipmans had amassed a large, significant collection that was highly regarded for its quality and scope.
During the early 1950s, the Lipmans also began actively collecting sculpture, focusing upon American contemporary sculptors. In the late 1950s they created the Howard W. Lipman Foundation, with an initial inventory of forty sculptures and three paintings by contemporary American artists. The purpose of the foundation was to acquire significant works by emerging American sculptors and to make them available through loans or donations to various art institutions.
In 1965 the Howard W. Lipman Foundation approached the Whitney Museum of American Art with a proposal to coordinate the foundation's efforts and goals with the museum's contemporary sculpture program. The foundation offered a majority of its growing collection of sculpture and acquisition funds towards the development of the evolving permanent collection of the Whitney Museum of American Art. Thereafter, the Howard W. Lipman Foundation served in an advisory role to the museum's acquisitions, and the foundation supplied the necessary funds to acquire works of sculpture desired by the Whitney for its permanent collection.
In addition to their folk art and foundation collections, the Lipmans also acquired important works by Alexander Calder, Louise Nevelson, and David Smith, through their lifelong association and friendship with these artists. Many of these pieces were retained in the Lipman's personal collection throughout their lives.
Individually the Lipmans also expressed their interest in art through various means. Jean Lipman served as editor of Art in America magazine from 1940 to 1970, which provided her with continuous exposure to emerging artists and trends in American art. Jean Lipman's abiding interest in folk and contemporary art was also expressed through her voluminous writings. Throughout her life she wrote and edited highly acclaimed books and articles about major themes and artists in American art, and she was a recognized folk art authority and connoisseur. Some of her best known works include: The Flowering of American Folk Art; Rufus Porter, Yankee Wall Painter; and Calder's Universe.
Jean Lipman, born in 1909, was also an amateur artist in her later years, creating paintings and assemblages that often dealt with the theme of "art about art." She was represented by a gallery in New York City, as well as one in Arizona, and she had several solo exhibitions.
Howard W. Lipman, born in 1905, showed an early interest in art. By the mid 1920s he had gone to Paris to study painting, but Lipman found himself more attracted to sculpture and he began studying with a German wood carver. In the late 1930s, after returning to the New York City area, Lipman began stone carving with the Clay Club on Eighth Street, adjacent to the Whitney Museum of American Art. He was represented by a New York City gallery and participated in local exhibitions.
Deciding that his sculptural talent was not sufficient for professional pursuit, Lipman began his business career as a stockbroker in Neuberger and Berman, a prominent New York investment management firm that he helped to establish in 1939. Lipman subsequently channeled his artistic endeavors toward collecting and supporting the work of established and emerging American sculptors. He also served on the boards of both the Whitney Museum of American Art and the Archives of American Art.
Howard and Jean Lipman maintained long and close relationships with three prominent American artists: Alexander Calder, Louise Nevelson, and David Smith. Jean Lipman, in particular, was involved in promoting and documenting Calder and his works through numerous articles, books, and exhibitions that she helped produce as editor of the magazine Art in America and publications director for the Whitney Museum of American Art. Calder's Universe, which she edited to accompany a major Whitney Museum of American Art retrospective exhibition of his works in 1976, was considered by Calder to be his "official" biography. The book went to fourteen printings, one of the largest ever, in the history of art books.
The Lipmans were also great admirers of Louise Nevelson and her work. They purchased her artwork for their own collection, as well as donating pieces to various art museums and institutions. Jean Lipman wrote articles about Nevelson and edited the book, Nevelson's World.
David Smith and the Lipmans established a friendship in the late 1950s that lasted until Smith's untimely death in May 1965. The Lipmans purchased several Smith sculptures, which they placed on the grounds of their Wilton, Connecticut, home. They also purchased Smith works for donation to public institutions, such as the Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts.
The Lipmans retired to Carefree, Arizona, a private residential community renown for its sensitivity to ecologically-based, architectural design. Howard Lipman died in 1992. Jean Lipman remained active in art and community affairs until her death in 1998.
Scope and Content Note
The Howard W. and Jean Lipman papers measure 46.2 linear feet and span the years 1916 to 2000. A copy of an 1848 brochure, retained by Jean Lipman in her research and writings files accounts for the early span date listed in the title of the collection. The bulk dates for the collection are 1932 to 1992. The records include correspondence, notes and printed material that served as research and reference material, along with some financial material that documents the art collecting activities and interests of the Lipmans. The collection also contains writing and editorial material used by Jean Lipman in her dual roles as an editor for Art in America magazine and as a respected author.
The Personal Files describe the social activities and associations of the Lipmans and include biographical information, personal and family correspondence, gift giving activities, the art career of Jean Lipman, and relationships maintained by the Lipmans with various art organizations.
The Howard and Jean Lipman Art Collection Files describe the art collecting activities and interests of the Lipmans throughout their lifetime. The General Files section consists of reference files on art organizations and galleries with whom the Lipmans maintained relationships. Also included are particular topics or exhibitions of interest to the Lipmans. The Sculptors and Painters of Interest section served as reference files about the activities of artists in whom the Lipmans were interested and whose works they owned, or considered owning. The Folk Art Collection section documents the collecting and purchasing activities of the Lipmans as they amassed and then subsequently sold their two significant folk art collections.
The Artists Files document the friendship and projects that developed between the Lipmans and three major American artists: Alexander Calder, Louise Nevelson, and David Smith. Of special interest to researchers will be some original Calder artwork mixed into the correspondence between the Lipmans and Calder, as well as drawings, sketches, prints, and posters found in the associated oversize folder. Also found in the Calder subseries are some proofs from Calder's Circus, edited by Jean Lipman.
The Research and Writing Files is divided into five sections dealing with research and writing projects undertaken by Jean Lipman. The first three sections deal with biographical projects that resulted in books or articles about three significant American primitive artists: Jurgan Frederick Huge, Rufus Porter, and Samuel Wood Gaylor. The fourth section deals with writing projects that resulted in the publication of several generalized books on the topic of American folk art. The final section consists of materials associated with the published articles and other authored works of Jean Lipman on a variety of American art topics.
The Art in America Editorial Files consists of editorial material maintained by Jean Lipman during her tenure (1941-1971) as editor of Art in America. The Financial Files reflect the early financial activities of the magazine during the brief period when the Lipmans owned it.
During the period that Jean Lipman served as editor, a variety of distinguished art historians, artists, architects, novelists, and poets contributed articles, columns, or artwork to the magazine. A sampling of correspondents that can be found in the general correspondence of this series include: Joseph Albers, Marcel DuChamp, John Dos Passos, Nelson Rockefeller, Charles Sheeler, and Andrew Wyeth. The General Correspondence Files also document the two subsequent changes of ownership and the growth of subscribers that occurred during the period of Lipman's editorship.
Editorial material related to individual magazine issues is found within this series, as well as information pertaining to the innovative advertising and special projects undertaken by the magazine as it sought to expand its readership and prestige. The Art in America series also chronicles the changes at the magazine that led to Lipman's resignation as editor in 1971.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as five series. Arrangement is generally alphabetical by subject heading or type of material. Items within folders are arranged chronologically by year.
Series 1: Personal Files (Boxes 1-3; 3 linear ft.)
Series 2: Howard and Jean Lipman Art Collection (Boxes 3-15; 12 linear ft.)
Series 3: Artists Files (Boxes 15-18, 46-47, OV 50-52; 3.6 linear ft.)
Series 4: Research and Writings Files (Boxes 18-28, 48; OV 50, 53; 10.3 linear ft.)
Series 5: Art in America Editorial Files (Boxes 28-45; 49, OV 50; 17.3 linear ft.)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms:
Subjects:
Calder, Alexander, 1898-1976; Gaylor, Wood, 1883-1957; Huge, Jurgan Frederick, 1809-1878; Smith, David, 1906-1965; Porter, Rufus, 1792-1884
Subjects-Topical:
Art -- Collectors and collecting -- New York (State) -- New York; Sculpture, Modern -- 20th century -- United States; Art, Primitive; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Folk art -- United States; Sculptors
Names:
Lipman, Jean, 1909-
Provenance
The papers of Howard and Jean Lipman were initially donated to the Archives of American Art by Howard and Jean Lipman from 1965-1989. Subsequent additions to the original gift were made by Jean Lipman in 1998 and by Peter and Beverly Lipman in 2001. Several small portions of these early accessions were microfilmed.
An associated gift that was originally accessioned as the Art in America Magazine Records was made by Howard and Jean Lipman from 1970-1973. This group, which largely consisted of Jean Lipman's editorial files from her years as editor of the magazine, was subsequently merged with the Howard W. and Jean Lipman records in 2004.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Personal Files, 1954-2000, undated, Series 1:; (Boxes 1-3, 3 linear feet)
  This series includes biographical information, family and personal correspondence, organizational membership information, gifts and donations to organizations, newspaper and magazine articles that detail the joint and individual activities of the Lipmans, photographs, and memorial items. Items are arranged alphabetically by subject headings. Within folders, material is arranged chronologically by year.
  - Archives of American Art, 1959-1973 (Box 1)
  - ASU Award to Jean Lipman, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Information, Lipman, Howard W., 1948-1981, undated (Box 1)
  - Biographical Information, Lipman, Jean, 1949-1999, undated (Box 1)
  - Carefree, Ariz., Residence, 1982-1985, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Aldrich Museum of Contemporary Art, 1974-1981 (Box 1)
    - Archives of American Art, 1981-1994, undated (Box 1)
    - Christmas Cards, 1954-1983, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Family, 1958-1995 (Box 1)
    - Galerie Maeght, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Hallmark Cards, Inc., 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Letters of Condolence Regarding Howard W. Lipman, 1992-1993, undated (Box 1)
    - Letters of Condolence Regarding Jean Lipman, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1951-1998, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Osborn, Elodie and Robert, 1960-1977, undated (Box 1)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1961-1994, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Wolfe, Ruth, 1979-1984, 1995, undated (Box 1)
  - Gifts, Grants, and Donations (Box 1)
    - Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts, 1967-1992 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Related Material, 1956-1991, undated (Box 1)
    - Museum of American Folk Art, 1981-2000 (Box 1)
    - Notebook, 1959-1967, (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Photographs, circa 1959-1973, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Gifts, Grants, and Donations (Box 2)
    - Photographs, circa 1959-1973, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1965-1992, undated (Box 2)
  - Interview of Jean Lipman for Art in America Article, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Material about Jean Lipman's Artwork (Box 2)
    - Art Plate, Arizona State University, 1990-1992, undated (Box 2)
    - Benefit Show, Arizona State University, 1993-1995 (Box 2)
    - Benefit Show, Museum of American Folk Art, 1981 (Box 2)
    - "Carefree" Christmas Card Designs, 1995-1997, undated (Box 2)
    - Catalogs and Exhibition Announcements, 1980-1994, undated (Box 2)
    - Elaine Horwitch Galleries, 1983-1992, undated (Box 2)
    - Exhibitions, Arizona State University, 1993-1996, undated (Box 2)
    - Frank J. Miele Gallery, 1991-1994, undated (Box 2)
    - Jay Johnson America's Folk Heritage Gallery, 1982-1987, undated (Box 2)
    - Photo-Collage Monoprints, 1987-1988, undated (Box 2)
    - Photographs and Negatives of Artwork, 1989, undated (Box 2)
    - Slides of Paintings and Collages, circa 1987-1997, (4 folders) (Box 2)
    - Tear Sheets of Images for "Art About Art" Designs, 1982-1996, undated (Box 2)
    - Transparencies of Artwork, undated (Box 2)
    - Wilton Historical Society Shows, 1980-1984, undated (Box 2)
    - Works in Private and Public Collections, 1987-1995, undated (Box 2)
  - Memberships, 1954-1963, undated (Box 2)
  - Memorials and Obituaries, Lipman, Howard W., 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - Memorials and Obituaries, Lipman, Jean, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Museum of Modern Art Tour of Private Collections, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Notes and Miscellaneous Material, 1956, 1991-1998, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs and Slides, 1962, 1994-1996, undated (Box 2)
  - Publicity Regarding Lipmans and Lipman Collection, 1954-2000, undated (Box 2)
  - Symposium Panel for Hirschl and Adler Folk Exhibition, 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art (Box 3)
    - Dismissal of Director, 1989-1990, undated (Box 3)
    - Exhibitions, 1962-1980, undated (Box 3)
    - Jean Lipman's Proposal for an Exhibition on Windows, 1968-1970, undated (Box 3)
    - Jean Lipman's Relationship with the Museum, 1983-1994, undated (Box 3)
    - Lippold, Richard, Offer of His Collection to the Museum, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Material, 1961-1992, undated (Box 3)
    - Printed Material Regarding Museum, 1960-1993, undated (Box 3)
    - Proposed Building Expansion, 1977-1985 (Box 3)
    - Refusal of Louise Nevelson Gift Offer, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Traveling Calder Exhibition, 1994 (Box 3)
- Howard and Jean Lipman Art Collection, 1954-2000, undated, Series 2:; (Boxes 3-15, 12 linear feet)
  The documents comprising the various subseries are a mixture of correspondence; loan agreements, biographical information, occasional photographs, slides, and study drawings; exhibition announcements, publicity, and commission material; financial documents relating to the purchase and sale of an individual artists' work; and miscellaneous printed matter about individual artists of interest to the Lipmans. Overall arrangement of the series is by subject matter. Material within folders is in chronological order by year. Further arrangement information is found under the individual headings for the subseries.
  The series is comprised of six subseries as follows:
  2.1: General Files, 1948-1997, undated
  2.2: Sculpture Collection Purchases, 1954-1989, undated
  2.3: Sculptors of Interest, 1950-1980, undated
  2.4: Painters of Interest, 1955-1978, undated
  2.5: American Folk Art Collection, 1848, 1938-1981, undated
  - General Files, 1948-1997, undated, 2.1:
    This subseries consists of reference files maintained on various galleries, art organizations and institutions, writings by art critics, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and general art topics. The arrangement is alphabetical by subject heading. Documents within folders are arranged chronologically by year.
    - A.I.R. (Artists in Residence, Inc.), 1973, undated (Box 3)
    - Aldrich Museum of Contemporary Art, 1969-1973 (Box 3)
    - Allan Frumkin Gallery, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Andre Emmerich Downtown, 1972-1974 (Box 3)
    - Anonymous Arts Recovery, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Appraisals, 1973-1992 (Box 3)
    - Arizona State University Exhibition, 1998-2000, undated (Box 3)
    - Artists Space, 1973-1974 (Box 3)
    - Automation House, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Betty Parsons, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Borgenicht Gallery, circa 1974 (Box 3)
    - Bykert Gallery, 1968-1973 (Box 3)
    - Canaday, John, Art Columns, 1963-1976 (Box 3)
    - Castelli, Leo, 1966-1975 (Box 3)
    - City of New York, Department of Parks, ("Sculpture of the Month" Program), 1966-1973, undated (Box 3)
    - City of New York, Recreation and Cultural Affairs Administration, 1967-1969 (Box 3)
    - Claude Bernard Exhibition, undated (Box 3)
    - "Contemporary American Sculpture: Selections I and II," 1966-1970, undated (Box 3)
    - Cordier and Ekstrom, 1969-1973 (Box 3)
    - Dwan Gallery, 1968-1971 (Box 3)
    - Erotic Art, 1973, undated (Box 3)
    - Exhibitions of European Sculpture, 1958-1962, undated (Box 3)
    - Exhibitions of the 1970s, 1971-1972, undated (Box 3)
    - 55 Mercer Gallery, undated (Box 3)
    - Finch College Museum of Art, 1970 (Box 3)
    - 14 Sculptors Gallery, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Genauer, Emily, Art Columns, 1961-1970 (Box 3)
    - Greenberg, Clement, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Group Exhibitions, 1948-1962, undated (Box 3)
    - Gruenebaum Gallery, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Haitian Art, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Hansen-Fuller Gallery, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Hirshhorn, Joseph, 1959-1979, undated (Box 3)
    - Howard and Jean Lipman Foundation, 1964-1986, undated (Box 3)
    - Howard Wise Gallery, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Invoices for Art Purchases, 1953-1984, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Jewish Museum, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - John Gibson, Inc., 1969-1970, undated (Box 3)
    - John Weber Gallery, 1972-1976 (Box 3)
    - Johnson, Philip C., 1966, 1970 (Box 3)
    - List, Albert A., 1965 (Box 3)
    - Loans of Artwork, Miscellaneous Institutions, circa 1963-1988 (Box 3)
    - Loans of Artwork, Whitney Museum of American Art, 1981-1997, undated (Box 3)
    - Kramer, Hilton, Art Columns, 1966-1993, undated (Box 3)
    - Lippincott, Inc., 1967-1972, undated (Box 3)
    - Lo Guidice, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Max Hutchinson Gallery, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
    - Museum of American Folk Art, 1966-1972, undated (Box 3)
    - Museum of Contemporary Art Exhibition, 1983 (Box 3)
    - O.K. Harris, 1966, 1970, undated (Box 4)
    - O'Doherty, Brian, Art Columns, 1963-1966, undated (Box 4)
    - Paley and Lowe, Inc., 1971 (Box 4)
    - Paula Cooper Gallery, 1971-1977 (Box 4)
    - "Primary Structures: Younger British and American Sculpture," 1966 (Box 4)
    - Reese Palley, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Richard Feigen Gallery, 1969-1970 (Box 4)
    - Scull, Robert and Ethel ("Spike"), 1966-1973, undated (Box 4)
    - Sculptors Guild, 1967-1971, undated (Box 4)
    - Sculpture Now, Inc., 1974-1977 (Box 4)
    - Sculpture, U.S.A. (Exhibition), 1959 (Box 4)
    - Sidney Janis Gallery, 1972, 1978 (Box 4)
    - Siegelaub, Seth, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Silvermine Guild of Artists, 1956-1966 (Box 4)
    - Sonnabend, 1970 (Box 4)
    - Staempfli, 1973, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Steichen, Edward, 1965-1973 (Box 4)
    - Storm King Art Center, 1972-1976, undated (Box 4)
    - 200 Years of American Sculpture (Exhibition), Whitney Museum of American Art, 1976 (Box 4)
    - Waddell Gallery, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Westport Community Art Association, 1956, 1962, undated (Box 4)
    - Willard Gallery, 1973 (Box 4)
    - William Zierler, Inc., 1974 (Box 4)
    - Zabriskie Gallery, 1972-1974 (Box 4)
  - Sculpture Collection Purchases, 1954-1989, undated, 2.2:
    The documents within this subseries consist of information about artists who were purchased or considered for purchase by the Howard W. Lipman Foundation, including biographical information; correspondence; invoices and receipts for purchases; announcements and invitations to exhibitions; and publicity and other miscellaneous printed material. Arrangement within the subseries is alphabetical by surname of the artist. Documents within folders are arranged chronologically by year.
    - Agostini, Peter, 1961-1973, undated (Box 4)
    - Albert, Calvin, 1960-1974, undated (Box 4)
    - Antonakos, Stephen, 1964-1978, undated (Box 4)
    - Artschwager, Richard, 1965-1980 (Box 4)
    - Asawa, Ruth, 1956-1971 (Box 4)
    - Baker, George, 1960-1971 (Box 4)
    - Bart, Robert, 1965, undated (Box 4)
    - Basen, Dan, 1958-1969, undated (Box 4)
    - Baskin, Leonard, 1958-1980, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Bell, Larry, 1963-1978, undated (Box 4)
    - Benton, Fletcher, 1966-1974, undated (Box 4)
    - Berlant, Anthony, 1963-1978, undated (Box 4)
    - Bertoia, Harry, 1960-1978, undated (Box 4)
    - Boghasian, Varujan, 1963-1979 (Box 4)
    - Bolomey, Roger, 1964-1968, undated (Box 4)
    - Bontecou, Lee, 1959-1975, undated (Box 4)
    - Brody, Joel, 1964-1973, undated (Box 4)
    - Broner, Robert, 1955-1962 (Box 4)
    - Byars, James, 1961-1971 (Box 4)
    - Calder, Alexander, 1971-1978, undated (Box 4)
    - Chamberlin, John, 1958-1989, undated (Box 4)